Guide to the Herbert Aptheker Papers, 1842-1999, (bulk 1934-1994)
Department of Special Collections
- Series 2. Aptheker Articles, Manuscripts, and Notes
  - Aptheker, Herbert. Ideas in our time: Racism and human experimentation, 1974, tms (25 p.) (Box 106, Folder 21)
  - Aptheker, Herbert. Ideas in our time: Sterilization, experimentation, & imperialism, part I: sterilization, 1974, tms (20 p.) (Box 106, Folder 22)
  - Aptheker, Herbert. Lenin and the last stage of capitalism, 1974, tms (11 p.) (Box 106, Folder 23)
  - Aptheker, Herbert. Lenin's imperialism: how relevant today, 1974, tms (16 p.) (Box 106, Folder 24)
  - Aptheker, Herbert. Marxism, religion, & revolution. -- In N.L. Gupta, ed. Transition from capitalism to socialism and other essays. -- New Delhi: Kalamkar Prakashan Pvt., Ltd., 1974 (Box 106, Folder 25)
  - Aptheker, Herbert. On Nixon and Watergate, 1974 (Box 106, Folder 26)
  - Aptheker, Herbert. Preface & additional references for American Negro slave revolts, 1974, tms (2 p.) (Box 106, Folder 27)
  - Aptheker, Herbert. Review of Atheism in Christianity by Ernst Bloch. -- In Journal of American Academy of Religion, 1974 (Box 106, Folder 28)
  - Aptheker, Herbert. Ideas in our time, 1974 (Box 106, Folder 29)
  - Published articles and letters by Herbert Aptheker, 1974 (Box 106, Folder 30)
  - CIA in Columbia, 1974 (Box 106, Folder 31)
  - Correspondence of W.E.B. Du Bois, vol. 1: selection, 1877 - 1934: publicity & reviews, 1974 (Box 106, Folder 32)
  - Correspondence of W.E.B. Du Bois, vol. 1: reviews, 1974 (Box 106, Folder 33)
  - Reviews of W.E.B. Du Bois bibliography, 1974 (Box 106, Folder 34)
  - Documentary history of the Negro people in the United States, vol. 3: dust jacket blurbs, 1974, tms (2 p.) (Box 106, Folder 35)
  - Documentary history of the Negro people in the United States, vol. 3: reviews, 1974 (Box 106, Folder 36)
  - Documentary history of the Negro people in the United States, vol. 3: index, 1974 (Box 106, Folder 37)
  - The education of Black people: reviews, 1974 (Box 106, Folder 38)
  - Reviews of Herbert Aptheker, 1974 (Box 106, Folder 39)
  - Herbert Aptheker: biographical information, 1974 (Box 106, Folder 40)
  - Chataqua Institution, 1974 July (Box 107, Folder 1)
  - Afro-American history course, Hostos Community College, 1974 Fall (Box 107, Folder 2)
  - Editing historical papers: W.E.B. Du Bois, Association for the Study of Afro-American Life & History, Philadelphia, 1974 Oct. 25, ams (11 p.) (Box 107, Folder 3)
  - Notes, 1974 (Box 107, Folder 4)
  - Questions on Du Bois, 1974 (Box 107, Folder 5)
  - Statement of Black & White unity, 1974 (Box 107, Folder 6)
  - Lectures, 1974 (Box 107, Folder 7)
  - Center for Marxist Education: 4 lectures, 1974 (Box 107, Folder 8)
  - Hostos Community College, 1974 (Box 107, Folder 9)
  - Clippings, 1974 (Box 107, Folder 10)
  - Aptheker, Herbert. Black-White unity: a basic theme and need in United States history., 1975 Jan. 15, tms (11 p.) (Box 107, Folder 11)
  - Aptheker, Herbert. Racism by hook or by crook: or, Sidney rides again, 1975 Jan. 23, tms (4 p.) (Box 107, Folder 12)
  - Aptheker, Herbert. Afro-American people and the American revolution, 1975 Jan. 27, tms (5 p.) (Box 107, Folder 13)
  - Aptheker, Herbert. Class, sex, & race: some notes on European thinking from the Fifteenth through the Seventeenth Centuries, 1975 Jan., tms (11 p.) (Box 107, Folder 14)
  - Aptheker, Herbert. Review of Black protest: issues and tactics by Robert C. Dick. -- In Journal of American History, 1975 Jan., tms (2 p.) (Box 107, Folder 15)
  - Aptheker, Herbert. Ideas in our time: Senile capitalism, racism, and slavery, 1975 Jan., tms (2 p.) (Box 107, Folder 16)
  - Aptheker, Herbert. Some answers to questions. -- In Jewish Affairs, 1975 Jan. - Feb. (Box 107, Folder 17)
  - Aptheker, Herbert. The history of anti-racism in the United States. -- In Black Scholar. -- Vol. 6, no. 5, 1975 Jan. - Feb. (Box 107, Folder 18)
  - Aptheker, Herbert. The history of anti-racism in the United States. -- In Black Scholar. -- Vol. 6, no. 5, 1975 Jan. - Feb. (Box 107, Folder 19)
  - Aptheker, Herbert. Frederick Douglass and human liberation, 1975 Feb. 5, tms (4 p.) (Box 107, Folder 20)
  - Aptheker, Herbert. Blacks and the Revolutionary War. -- In World Magazine, 1975 Feb. 8 (Box 107, Folder 21)
  - Aptheker, Herbert. Let's set the record straight. -- In World Magazine, 1975 Mar. 29 (Box 107, Folder 22)
  - Aptheker, Herbert. Commentary on Conference on Slavery -- Queens College, 1975 Apr. 12, tms (22 p.) (Box 107, Folder 23)
    Includes notes.
  - Aptheker, Herbert. The CIA and the 'Free Press', 1975 May 10, tms (4 p.) (Box 107, Folder 24)
    Includes clippings.
  - Aptheker, Herbert. Ideas in our time: An intensified racist offensive, 1975 May 30, tms (12 p.) + an (Box 107, Folder 25)
  - Aptheker, Herbert. On the 30th anniversary of the defeat of Hitler fascism. -- In New World Review. -- Vol. 43, no. 3, 1975 May - June (Box 107, Folder 26)
  - Aptheker, Herbert. The class character of the American revolution. -- In World Marxist Review. -- Vol. 18, no. 7, 1975 July (Box 107, Folder 27)
  - Aptheker, Herbert. Review of The new Negro on campus by Raymond Wolters. -- In Journal of Ethnic Studies. -- Vol. 3, 1975 Summer (Box 107, Folder 28)
  - Aptheker, Herbert. Review of The new Negro on campus by Raymond Wolters: Black college rebellions of the 1920's, 1975 May, tms (4 p.) + an (Box 107, Folder 29)
    Includes reprint of published review in the Journal of Ethnic Studies, Vol. 3 (1975 Summer).
  - Aptheker, Herbert. Introduction, Vol. II Du Bois correspondence, 1975 Sept. 27, tms (4 p.) (Box 107, Folder 30)
  - Aptheker, Herbert. Zionism and racism. -- In Jewish Affairs, 1975 Sept. - Oct. (Box 107, Folder 31)
  - Aptheker, Herbert. Ideas in our time: United States imperialism and its intelligence agencies, 1975 Oct. 6, tms (13 p.) (Box 107, Folder 32)
  - Aptheker, Herbert. Minnesota Forum debate, 1975 Nov. 14, tms (10 p.) (Box 107, Folder 33)
  - Aptheker, Herbert. Review of Stephen B. Oakes The fires of Jubilee. -- In American Historical Review, 1975 Nov. 24, tms (1 p.) (Box 107, Folder 34)
  - Aptheker, Herbert. Introduction ot Du Bois book reviews, 1975 Dec. 15, tms (3 p.) (Box 107, Folder 35)
  - Aptheker, Herbert. Letters to the Editor, 1975 (Box 107, Folder 36)
  - Book reviews of Herbert Aptheker, 1975 (Box 107, Folder 37)
  - Bibliography on democracy in the United States, 1975 June (Box 107, Folder 38)
  - Yale University [1 of 3], 1975 - 1976 (Box 107, Folder 39)
  - Yale University [2 of 3], 1975 - 1976 (Box 108, Folder 1)
  - Yale University [3 of 3], 1975 - 1976 (Box 108, Folder 2)
  - Clippings re: Yale appointment [1 of 2], 1975 - 1976 (Box 108, Folder 3)
  - Clippings re: Yale appointment [2 of 2], 1975 - 1976 (Box 108, Folder 4)
  - Grove Press royalty statement, 1975 June 30 (Box 108, Folder 5)
  - Grove Press royalty statement, 1975 June 30 (Box 108, Folder 5)
  - Aptheker, Herbert. The correspondence of W.E.B. Du Bois: Vol. I: book sleeve, 1975 (Box 108, Folder 6)
  - University of Massachusetts Press. Fall books & complete catalog, 1975 (Box 108, Folder 7)
  - Kraus Reprint Co. Afro-American studies: essential publications available in print: catalog, [ca. 1975] (Box 108, Folder 8)
  - Kraus-Thompson Royalty statements, 1975 Sept. 30 (Box 108, Folder 9)
  - Empire Savings Bank transaction records, 1975 Jan. - May (Box 108, Folder 10)
  - Miscellaneous correspondence, 1975 (Box 108, Folder 11)
  - Flyers & announcements, 1975 (Box 108, Folder 12)
  - Publicity, 1975 (Box 108, Folder 13)
  - Philadelphia Social Science forum lecture flyer, notes, & clippings. On the American revolution, 1975 Jan. 9 (Box 108, Folder 14)
  - Aptheker, Herbert. Remarks, Jewish Affairs dinner, Statler-Hilton Hotel, New York City, 1975 Jan. 12, tms (6 p.) with an (Box 108, Folder 15)
  - Bicentennial lecture, Hostos Community College, 1975 Feb. 25 (Box 108, Folder 16)
  - Center for Afro-American Studies, UCLA. Seminar, 1975 Mar. 5 (Box 108, Folder 17)
  - Lecture notes. Hofstra University. On the American revolution, 1975 Apr. 23 (Box 108, Folder 18)
  - Center for Marxist Education lecture notes & flyer. On World War II: source, conduct, consequences, 1975 May - June (Box 108, Folder 19)
  - Aptheker, Herbert. The road to peace in the Middle East: speech given at Hotel George Washington, New York City, 1975 June 20, tms (15 p.) (Box 108, Folder 20)
    Includes speech printed in Jewish Affairs (1975 May-June).
  - Aptheker, Herbert. Chicago XXI convention CPUSA amphitheatre: speech. On Politics, 1975 June 29, tms (4 p.) (Box 108, Folder 21)
  - Ramapo College lecture program and notes on racism, 1975 Sept. 17 (Box 108, Folder 22)
  - Aptheker, Herbert. Notes for remarks at C.C. meeting, 1975 Oct. 5 (Box 108, Folder 23)
  - Aptheker, Herbert. Notes for racism and the arts meeting, 1975 Oct. 23 (Box 108, Folder 24)
  - Aptheker, Herbert. On pornography, 1975 Nov. 5, tms (2 p.) (Box 108, Folder 25)
  - Aptheker, Herbert. On slavery in the U.S. and islands of the Caribbean: Rhode Island College lecture flyer and notes, 1975 Dec. 10 (Box 108, Folder 26)
  - Newsletter of the Radical Historians Caucus, 1975 Mar. (Box 108, Folder 27)
  - Aptheker, Herbert. On World War II: notes, 1975 June 6 (Box 108, Folder 28)
  - Clippings, 1975 (Box 108, Folder 29)
  - Miscellany, 1975 (Box 108, Folder 30)
  - Souvenir map of the Charles Caldwell Centennial March, 1975 Oct. 11 (Box 108, Folder 31)
  - Aptheker, Herbert. Zum klassencharakter der Amerikanischen revolution. -- In Kontakt. -- Vol. 1, no. 9, 1976 Jan. - Feb. (Box 108, Folder 32)
  - Aptheker, Herbert. The history of Anti-racism in the United States. -- In The Black Scholar. -- Vol. 6, no. 5, 1976 Jan. - Feb. (Box 108, Folder 33)
  - Aptheker, Herbert. Israel: towards peace with honor: presented at Jewish Affairs 4th annual dinner, 1976 Feb. 15, tms (5 p.) + an + clippings (Box 108, Folder 34)
  - Aptheker, Herbert. Comments on main draft main resolution, 1976 Apr., tms (1 p.) (Box 108, Folder 35)
  - Aptheker, Herbert. On the 31st anniversary of European victory over fascism: statement for TASS, 1976 May 7, tms (1 p.) (Box 108, Folder 36)
  - Aptheker, Herbert. Comparative perspectives on slavery in New World plantation societies: commentary, New York Academy of Sciences conference, 1976 May 26, tms (6 p.) (Box 108, Folder 37)
  - Aptheker, Herbert. On Walter Lowenfels: tms + speech notes, 1976 July 9, tms (1 p.) + an (Box 109, Folder 1)
  - Aptheker, Herbert. Report for TASS on the Conference of European Communist Parties, 1976 July 10, tms (2 p.) (Box 109, Folder 2)
  - Aptheker, Herbert. Black people and 1976 elections: lecture notes for speech given in Miami, Florida, 1976 Sept. 5, tms (2 p.) (Box 109, Folder 3)
  - Aptheker, Herbert. Book review of Simon Gerson's Biography of Peter Cacchione. -- In Daily World, 1976 Sept. 13, tms (5 p.) (Box 109, Folder 4)
  - Aptheker, Herbert. Introduction to Robert Steigerwald book, 1976 Sept., tms (3 p.) (Box 109, Folder 5)
  - Aptheker, Herbert. Anti-racism in the United States prior to the Civil War: presented at ASA-A LH, Chicago, 1976 Oct. 30, incomplete tms (1 p.) (Box 109, Folder 6)
    Includes flyer and program.
  - Aptheker, Herbert. Anti-racism with Herbert Aptheker. -- In Marho Newsletter. -- Vol. 2, no. 3, [ca. 1976 Nov.] (Box 109, Folder 7)
  - Aptheker, Herbert. Elitism, racism, & lying, 1976 Dec. 6, tms (4 p.) (Box 109, Folder 8)
    Includes clippings referred to in manuscript.
  - Aptheker, Herbert. A racist lie exposed. -- In World Magazine, 1976 Dec. 18 (Box 109, Folder 9)
  - Aptheker, Herbert. Ideas in our time: The Abolitionist movement, 1976, tms (9 p.) (Box 109, Folder 10)
  - Aptheker, Herbert. The American revolution, [ca. 1976], tms (6 p.) (Box 109, Folder 11)
    Includes business card from Nicolai Kuryumov and note.
  - Aptheker, Herbert. The Mid-East, Israel, and the 1976 elections: presented at Jewish Affairs meeting, 1976, tms (10 p.) (Box 109, Folder 12)
  - Aptheker, Herbert. Notes on Black liberation, [ca. 1976], tms (4 p.) (Box 109, Folder 13)
  - Aptheker, Herbert. Zionism and racism, [ca. 1976], tms (8 p.) (Box 109, Folder 14)
  - Letters to the Editor, 1976 (Box 109, Folder 15)
  - Book reviews, 1976 (Box 109, Folder 16)
  - Aptheker bibliographic information. Committee to Elect Aptheker to the Senate, [ca. 1976] (Box 109, Folder 17)
  - Aptheker, Herbert. Publication list, 1976 June 24 (Box 109, Folder 18)
  - Proposed table of contents for Aptheker Reader, 1976 July 22 (Box 109, Folder 19)
  - Aptheker, Herbert. Notes on citations, [ca. 1976] (Box 109, Folder 20)
  - Speaking engagements, 1976 (Box 109, Folder 21)
  - Aptheker, Herbert. Lecture notes, 1976 (Box 109, Folder 22)
  - Aptheker, Herbert. Slavery: unfinished business of the revolution: some recent interpretations: lecture notes for Northern Illinois University, 1976 Apr. 13 (Box 109, Folder 23)
  - Aptheker, Herbert. History of forcible expansion: lecture notes, 1976 July (Box 109, Folder 24)
  - University of Iowa permission for recording presentation, 1976 June 1 (Box 109, Folder 25)
  - Kraus Reprint Co. Drop ship order, 1976 Oct. 1 (Box 109, Folder 26)
  - Agreement between Kraus-Thompson Organization & Shirley Graham Du Bois re: W.E.B. Du Bois writings. Exhibit A., [ca. 1976] (Box 109, Folder 27)
  - Agreement between Kraus-Thompson Organization & Shirley Graham Du Bois re: W.E.B. Du Bois writings. Exhibit A., [ca. 1976] (Box 109, Folder 27)
  - A history of the American people by Herbert Aptheker: announcement of publication. -- In Journal of American History, 1976 Dec. (Box 109, Folder 28)
  - Radical History Review. -- Vol. 3, no. 3, 1976 Spring (Box 109, Folder 29)
  - Note by unidentified author, [ca. 1976] (Box 109, Folder 30)
  - Photograph of Herbert Aptheker, Leon Litwack, Bettye Thomas at Univ. of Iowa, 1976 (Box 109, Folder 31)
  - Historical news and comment. -- In Journal of American History. -- Vol. 63, 1976 Sept. (Box 109, Folder 32)
  - Aptheker for Senate [1 of 2], 1976 (Box 109, Folder 33)
  - Aptheker for Senate [2 of 2], 1976 (Box 109, Folder 34)
  - Clippings, 1976 (Box 109, Folder 35)
  - Review of The early years of the republic by Herbert Aptheker, 1976 (Box 109, Folder 36)
  - Miscellany, 1976 (Box 109, Folder 37)
  - Aptheker, Herbert. Freedom, equality, and Jewish people: myths and realities: presented at Jewish Affairs dinner, 1977 Jan. 23, tms (12 p.) (Box 110, Folder 1)
  - Aptheker, Herbert. Robert W. Dunn, 1977 Jan. 24, tms (1 p.) (Box 110, Folder 2)
    Includes 1 clipping
  - Aptheker, Herbert. Statement for TASS on nuclear disarmament, 1977 Feb. 1, ams (1 p.) (Box 110, Folder 3)
  - Aptheker, Herbert. U.S. foreign policy from Kennedy to Carter, 1977 Feb. 3, tms (2 p.) + an (4 p.) (Box 110, Folder 4)
  - Aptheker, Herbert. Human rights, dissent, & revolution, 1977 Feb. 14, tms (8 p.) (Box 110, Folder 5)
  - Aptheker, Herbert. Anti-racism in the United States prior to the Civil War: lecture delivered at Vassar College., 1977 Feb., tms (13 p.) (Box 110, Folder 6)
  - Aptheker, Herbert. On academic freedom, 1977 Mar. 5, tms (2 p.) + tls (Box 110, Folder 7)
  - Aptheker, Herbert. What are the important questions that radical historians should ask about the 1930's?, 1977 Mar., tms (2 p.) (Box 110, Folder 8)
  - Aptheker, Herbert. Anti-communism & history writing, 1977 Apr. 11, tms (4 p.) (Box 110, Folder 9)
  - Aptheker, Herbert. Illiteracy & human rights, 1977 Apr. 14, tms (5 p.) (Box 110, Folder 10)
  - Aptheker, Herbert. Freedom of speech, human rights, and the U.S. government, 1977 Apr. 19, tms (5 p.) (Box 110, Folder 11)
  - Aptheker, Herbert. The struggle against racism: myths & realities. -- In Political Affairs, 1977 Apr. (Box 110, Folder 12)
  - Aptheker, Herbert. To read and write is a human right. -- In Daily World, 1977 May 3 (Box 110, Folder 13)
  - Aptheker, Herbert. Aims of ruling class versions of history. -- In Daily World, 1977 May 10 (Box 110, Folder 14)
  - Aptheker, Herbert. On pornography, 1977 May 17, tms (3 p.) (Box 110, Folder 15)
  - Aptheker, Herbert. Human rights -- myths and realities, 1977 June 5, tms (4 p.) (Box 110, Folder 16)
  - Dunham, Barrows. Transcript of interview between Herbert Aptheker & Fred Zimring, 1977 July 5, 16 p. (2 copies) (Box 110, Folder 17)
  - Aptheker, Herbert. Lecture given at Martin Luther King, Jr. Auditorium, New York City, 1977 July 6, tms ( 7 p.) (Box 110, Folder 18)
  - Aptheker, Herbert. On Central European socialism, 1977 July, tms ( 3 p.) (Box 110, Folder 19)
  - Aptheker, Herbert. The influence of the Great October revolution & of the U.S.S.R. upon the United States, 1977 Aug. 16, tms ( 5 p.) (Box 110, Folder 20)
  - Aptheker, Herbert. The New York Times (still) dislikes Marxism, 1977 Sept. 1, tms ( 2 p.) (Box 110, Folder 21)
  - Aptheker, Herbert. The New York Times (still) dislikes Marxism, 1977 Sept. 1, tms ( 2 p.) (Box 110, Folder 22)
  - Aptheker, Herbert. Lecture prepared for presentation to San Jose City Council, 1977 Oct. 4, tms ( 2 p.) (Box 110, Folder 23)
  - Aptheker, Herbert. Notes for untitled lecture given at Temple, 1977 Oct. 14 (Box 110, Folder 24)
  - Aptheker, Herbert. Racism, affirmative action, & the Bolshevik revolution. -- p. 3-5. -- In Jewish Affairs, 1977 Sept. - Oct. (Box 110, Folder 25)
  - Aptheker, Herbert. Comments, Southern Historical Association, New Orleans, 1977 Nov. 10 (Box 110, Folder 26)
  - Aptheker, Herbert. Radicalism, disease, & psychosurgergy, 1977 Nov. 15, tms (2 p.) (Box 110, Folder 27)
  - Aptheker, Herbert. Psychosurgergy & senile capitalism. -- In P.W., 1977 Nov. 26 (Box 110, Folder 28)
  - Aptheker, Herbert. American history: illusion and reality, 1977 Nov. 28, tms (7 p.) (Box 110, Folder 29)
  - Aptheker, Herbert. The U.S. & the 'appeasement' of Hitler, 1977 Dec. 13, tms (3 p.) (Box 110, Folder 30)
  - Aptheker, Herbert. Curriculum vita: Herbert Aptheker, [ca. 1977], tms (3 p.) (Box 110, Folder 31)
  - Aptheker, Herbert. The history of anti-racism in the U.S.: some introductory remarks, [ca. 1977], tms (15 p.) (Box 110, Folder 32)
  - Aptheker, Herbert. Human rights, dissent, and revolution. -- In Daily World, [ca. 1977], tms (15 p.) (Box 110, Folder 33)
  - Aptheker, Herbert. On the expansion of the American Institute for Marxist Studies, [ca. 1977], tms (3 p.) (Box 110, Folder 34)
  - Aptheker, Herbert. Racism & the law in the U.S.: a series of 14 lectures, [ca. 1977], tms (8 p.) (Box 110, Folder 35)
  - Aptheker, Herbert. Contents to Vol. III of Correspondence, [ca. 1977], tms (19 p.) wanting pages 1 & 9 (Box 110, Folder 36)
  - Aptheker, Herbert. My own writings [1 of 2], 1977 - 1982 (Box 110, Folder 37)
  - Aptheker, Herbert. My own writings [2 of 2], 1977 - 1982 (Box 110, Folder 38)
  - Aptheker, Herbert. Letters to the Editor, 1977 (Box 110, Folder 39)
  - Articles re: Herbert Aptheker, 1977 (Box 110, Folder 40)
  - Book reviews, 1977 (Box 110, Folder 41)
  - Note on Partington matter, 1977 Jan. 24 (Box 110, Folder 42)
  - Press releases, 1977 (Box 110, Folder 43)
  - Publicity, 1977 (Box 110, Folder 44)
  - Speaking engagements, 1977 (Box 111, Folder 1)
  - American Education Research Association, 1977 (Box 111, Folder 2)
  - AIMS, 1977 (Box 111, Folder 3)
  - Association for the Study of Afro-American Life & History 62nd annual meeting: correspondence & program, 1977 Oct. (Box 111, Folder 4)
  - Communist Party of the USA statement on current policies of the Morning Freiheit, 1977 May 11 (Box 111, Folder 5)
  - Organization of American Historians newsletter, 1977 Jan. (Box 111, Folder 6)
  - Genovese, Eugene. A reply to criticism. -- In Radical History Review, 1977 Winter, 2 copies (Box 111, Folder 7)
  - Patterson, William L. Au revoir but not goodbye, 1977 July 6, tms (2 p.) (Box 111, Folder 8)
  - Clippings, 1977 (Box 111, Folder 9)
  - Clippings, 1977 (Box 111, Folder 10)
  - Miscellaneous, 1977 (Box 111, Folder 11)
  - Miscellaneous, 1977 (Box 111, Folder 12)
  - Aptheker, Herbert. The U.S. and Hitler on the eve of WWII. -- In P.W., 1978 Jan. 7 (Box 111, Folder 13)
  - Aptheker, Herbert. The dialectics of the Black liberation movement, 1978 Feb. 21, tms (14 p.) (Box 111, Folder 14)
  - Aptheker, Herbert. No freedom of speech for Nazis and the KKK. -- p. 26-29. -- In Political Affairs, 1978 Apr., 4 p. (Box 111, Folder 15)
  - Aptheker, Herbert. The crisis in the capitalist world., 1978 May, tms (10 p.) (Box 111, Folder 16)
  - Aptheker, Herbert. The present situation in the United States, 1978 June, tms (19 p.) (Box 111, Folder 17)
  - Aptheker, Herbert. W.E.B. Du Bois: 1868-1963, 1978 June, tms (17 p.) (Box 111, Folder 18)
  - Aptheker, Herbert. Reconstruction: the foresight of Du Bois. -- p. 189. -- In Wilson Quarterly, 1978 Summer (Box 111, Folder 19)
  - Aptheker, Herbert. Another blow against racism and elitism, 1978 Aug. 31, tms (2 p.) + clipping (Box 111, Folder 20)
  - Aptheker, Herbert. The Middle East: what now?. -- p. 5-8. -- In Jewish Affairs, 1978 Aug. - Sept. (Box 111, Folder 21)
  - Aptheker, Herbert. On Carter and nuclear arms, 1978 Oct. 19, ams (1 l.) (Box 111, Folder 22)
  - Aptheker, Herbert. Letter to the Editor re: Milton, Mill, & Cohen. -- p. 394. -- In The Nation, 1978 Oct. 21 (Box 111, Folder 23)
  - Aptheker, Herbert. Racism and freedom of the press, 1978 Dec. 8 (Box 111, Folder 24)
  - Aptheker, Herbert. Review of Randall M. Miller, ed.'s Dear master: letters of a slave family, 1978, tms (3 p.) (Box 111, Folder 25)
  - AIMS Board meeting minutes, 1978 Oct. 7 (Box 111, Folder 26)
  - Organization of American Historians newsletter. -- Vol. 6, no. 1, 1978 July (Box 111, Folder 27)
  - Roediger, David. The radical heritage of W.E.B. Du Bois. -- In The Progressive, 1978 Oct. (Box 111, Folder 28)
  - Smith, Ralph S. Two centuries and twenty-four months: a chronicle of the struggle to desegregate the Boston public schools, [1978] (Box 111, Folder 29)
  - Talks, 1978 (Box 111, Folder 30)
  - Invitations, 1978 (Box 111, Folder 31)
  - Clippings, 1978 (Box 111, Folder 32)
  - Miscellaneous, 1978 (Box 111, Folder 33)
  - Aptheker, Herbert. Re: human rights. -- In Christian Century, 1979 Feb. 7-14 (Box 112, Folder 1)
  - Aptheker, Herbert. Review of Who financed Hitler by James Pool and Susan Pool. -- In Daily World, 1979 Feb. 22 (Box 112, Folder 2)
  - Aptheker, Herbert. Exposing still another anti-Soviet lie. -- p. 13. -- In Daily World, 1979 Feb. 24 (Box 112, Folder 3)
  - Aptheker, Herbert. Imperialism's intelligence. -- p. 63-68. -- In Labour Monthly, 1979 Feb. (Box 112, Folder 4)
  - Aptheker, Herbert. Valuable weapons for struggle. -- p. 12. -- In Daily World, 1979 Mar. 10 (Box 112, Folder 5)
  - Aptheker, Herbert. Imperialist propoganda refuted. -- p. 13. -- In Daily World, 1979 Mar. 16 (Box 112, Folder 6)
  - Aptheker, Herbert. Crude racism and sexism emerging as key elements in right-wing drive, 1979 Mar. 21 (Box 112, Folder 7)
  - Aptheker, Herbert. Thirty years of a socialist Germany: a view from the United States, 1979 Mar. 30 (Box 112, Folder 8)
  - Aptheker, Herbert. Review of Daniel De Leon by L. Glen Seretan, 1979 Apr. 5, tms (2 p.) + an (2 p.) + tls (1 p.) (Box 112, Folder 9)
  - Aptheker, Herbert. Review of Dirty work: the CIA in Western Europe. -- p. 13. -- In Daily World, 1979 Apr. 6 (Box 112, Folder 10)
  - Aptheker, Herbert. The oil cartel and South Africa, 1979 Apr. 7 (Box 112, Folder 11)
  - Aptheker, Herbert. The lesson of Iran. -- p. 9. -- In Daily World, 1979 Apr. 11 (Box 112, Folder 12)
  - Aptheker, Herbert. Memorable meeting of U.S. historians. -- p. 26. -- In Daily World, 1979 Apr. 26 (Box 112, Folder 13)
  - Aptheker, Herbert. Review of Clyde & Sally Griffen's Natives and newcomers: the ordering of opportunity in Mid-Nineteenth Century Poughkeepsie. -- In The New York Historical Society Quarterly. -- Vol. LXIII, no. 2, 1979 Apr. (Box 112, Folder 14)